Guide to the Beaver Creek Ranch Company Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Beaver Creek Ranch Company papers
1882-1915
WA MSS S-1301
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.25
(3 boxes)
The papers contain correspondence, business, and legal papers documenting the history of the Beaver Creek Ranch Company. Subjects discussed include the managment of the ranch, cattle drivers, and the responsibilities of ranch owners.
Beaver Creek Ranch Company (Archulette City, Colo.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were purchased from Whitlock Farm Booksellers in 1959 with proceeds from the William Robertson Coe Fund for Western Americana.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Beaver Creek Ranch Company Papers document the organization and management of a cattle ranch in late nineteenth-century Colorado. They include chronologically arranged correspondence, business papers, legal documents, and printed material. The papers date from 1882 to 1915 with the bulk of material spanning the years 1884 to 1892.
The Beaver Creek Ranch Company was incorporated on May 21, 1884, in Washington, Litchfield County, Connecticut. According to its bylaws, the board of directors annually elected a president, treasurer, secretary, and superintendent. The superintendent, responsible for the management of the ranch, was the only officer required to live on the premises. The ranch was established in Ignacio, Colorado, on land acquired under terms of the 1862 Homestead Act. Ignacio had strong ties with the nearby boomtown of Durango, Colorado. The company remained in strong financial condition from 1884 to 1890, but, during the harsh winter of 1890-91, the ranch lost many cattle, forcing the stockholders to authorize the directors to dissolve the company in 1892.
The papers cover subjects relating to the development of southern Colorado, the lifestyles of the settlers, the financial management of cattle ranches, and the responsibilities of ranch owners. The correspondence contains several letters describing cattle drives. Expense reports, inventories, and accounts add to the detailed picture of how cattle drives were managed and organized. Scattered through the correspondence are references to the Indian Affairs Commission, local Indians, and Mexican sheep runners. Major correspondents include Alpheus G. Baker, William J. Ford, and A. S. Swords.
The legal documents include papers of incorporation, homestead documentation, annual stockholder reports, and papers concerning cattle sales and brands. There are also two undated versions of the bylaws.
Accounts include ledger books, monthly and yearly statements, cash accounts, and miscellaneous daily records, which provide documentation of the ranch's management. The financial standing of the company can be traced monthly between 1884 and 1892. The bank records, tax records, inventories, and expense reports complement the accounts. The bills and receipts trace the company's needs and practices. Bills from merchants in Texas, New Mexico, and Colorado are present.
Printed material includes an Indian Affairs Commission proposal for contracts to supply Indians with food. Among the miscellaneous papers are an undated phrenological description of Helen R. Allen by Professor Hinnan and a genealogy of the Logan, Ford, and Leavett families.
Cattle trade -- Colorado; Cattle trails; Farm corporations -- Colorado; Ranches -- Colorado; Accounts -- United States; Ranchers -- Colorado; Baker, Alpheus G.; Ford, W. J. (William J.), active 1882-1915; Swords, A. S.; Beaver Creek Ranch Company (Archulette City, Colo.)
- Box and Folder List
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Correspondence, 1884-85 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - Correspondence, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - Correspondence, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
    - Correspondence, 1890-91 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1896-1916 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
    - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - BUSINESS AND LEGAL PAPERS
    - Accounts, 1884-92, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17-25)
    - Bank records, 1884-1901, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26-32)
    - Bills and receipts, 1884-93, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 33-55)
    - Expense reports, 1885-89, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Inventories, 1887-91 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Legal papers, 1882-92, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 58-65)
    - Ledgers, 1884-86 (Box 3, Folder 66-68)
    - Tax records, 1885-93 (Box 3, Folder 69-71)
  - ADDITIONAL PAPERS
    - Printed: Indian Affairs Proposal, Keenen & Sons livestock sale, 1888 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Genealogical chart, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Phrenological description, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Miscellaneous papers, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 75)